[Music]
start with the real number r between 0
and 1.
draw an infinite vertical line connected
to a horizontal line of length given by
the sum of the positive powers of r
which is a geometric series and thus
converges to a finite value
from the end of the horizontal line
build a staircase type diagram where the
stair heights are all one and the stair
depths are the positive powers of r so
that each stair platform gets narrower
this object has been called gabriel's
staircase it has an infinite perimeter
but encloses a finite area
let's compute the enclosed area in two
ways
first we decompose the staircase into
columns of rectangles the first one has
height 1 and width r so it contains an
area of 1 times r
the next one has height 2 and width r
squared so it contains an area of 2
times r squared
the third one has height three
and width r cubed so it encloses an area
of three times r cubed and the next one
encloses an area of four times r to the
fourth we continue this process forever
with narrower and narrower rectangles
giving an infinite sum for the area
we can also decompose the staircase into
rows of rectangles
the first such rectangle has height 1
and the width is the sum of the
geometric series with ratio r and first
term r which converges to r over 1 minus
r so the area enclosed is r over 1 minus
r
the second rectangle also has height 1
and this time the width is the geometric
series with ratio r and first term r
squared which converges to r squared
over 1 minus r so that the area is r
squared over 1 minus r
the next two rectangles are also of
height 1 and widths of geometric series
and thus they enclose areas of r cubed
over one minus r
and r to the fourth over one minus r
we again continue this process forever
with smaller and smaller rectangles
giving a different infinite sum for the
area
these two infinite sums can be shown to
both converge to a finite value because
r is between 0 and 1. the sums enclose
the same area so they must be equal thus
we have that the sum from one to
infinity of k r to the k
is equal to the sum from one to infinity
of r to the k over one minus r
but we can factor one minus r out of the
ladder sum leaving us with the geometric
series with ratio r and first term r
again which we know converges to r over
one minus r thus the sum from one to
infinity of k
times r to the k is equal to r over the
quantity one minus r squared provided r
is between zero and one
[Music]
you